{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In a painting by this artist, Ambrosio de Spinola receives the keys to a besieged Dutch town\nfrom Justin of Nassau. This artist of The Surrender of Breda also painted The Rokeby Venus. A\ndwarf in a dress is one of the title attendants of the Infanta Margarita in a painting by this artist.\nFor 10 points, name this Spanish artist of Las Meninas.",
      "answer": [
        "Diego Velazquez",
        "Velazquez",
        "Diego Rodriguez de Silva y Velazquez"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This instrument was invented by a Belgian seeking a solution to the problem of clarinets\nraising their pitch when overblown. This instrument was played by Cannonball Adderley as well\nas the composer of Giant Steps, John Coltrane. For 10 points, name this classical and jazz\ninstrument which has alto and tenor varieties and is a woodwind made out of brass.",
      "answer": [
        "saxophone",
        "sax"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man refused to continue working on the film The Golden Age after denouncing his\ncollaborator, Luis Buñuel, for \"communism and atheism,\" three years after he completed Un\nChien Andalou (pr. uh shee-EN on-da-LOO) For 10 points, name this Spanish surrealist who\npainted The Persistence of Memory, which shows several melting watches.",
      "answer": [
        "Salvador Dali",
        "Dali"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting by this man was ordered defaced by the Council of Trent, leading to the man who\naltered his work being known as \"The Breeches-Painter.\" Daniele da Volterra added loincloths to\ncover the nudity in this man's The Last Judgment. For 10 points, name this painter who worked\nlying on his back on a scaffold to decorate the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel.",
      "answer": [
        "Michelangelo",
        "Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni",
        "Buonarroti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A sculpture group by this artist depicts an incident in which Eustache de Saint Pierre led six\nmen into captivity in 1347 following a battle with Edward III. The most iconic piece by this\nsculptor was part of his exhibition The Gates of Hell and represents Dante planning the Divine\nComedy. For 10 points, name this sculptor of The Burghers of Calais and The Thinker.",
      "answer": [
        "Auguste Rodin",
        "Rodin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An opera from this country is about a peasant who averts an invasion by leading the Polish\narmy into a forest. This country's nationalist group \"The Mighty Handful\" composed Pictures at\nan Exhibition and Flight of the Bumblebee. For 10 points, name this home country of Modest\nMussorgky (pr. moo-SORG-skee) and Rimsky-Korsakov (pr. RIM-skee-CORE-suh-koff).",
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "question": "American \"shows\" described by this word featured stock characters such as Mr. Bones and\nperformers dressed in blackface. In the middle ages, this word generally described people such as\nminnesingers (pr. MIN-eh-singers) and troubadours, who sang or played the harp, flute, or lute.\nFor 10 points, name these people who were travelling musicians of the middle ages.",
      "answer": [
        "minstrels"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An early practitioner of this art form was satirized as \"elevating\" it from a hot-air balloon in\nan engraving by Honoré Daumier (pr. oh-no-RAY dow-mee-EY). This art form was used to\ndepict The Steerage by Alfred Stieglitz and Moon and Half Dome by a later American leader of\nf/64 (\"eff sixty-four\"). For 10 points, name this art form used by Ansel Adams to produce prints.",
      "answer": "photography"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer was patronized by Cardinal Rudolf of Austria, to whom he dedicated his\nArchduke Trio. This composer wrapped his head in pillows and hid in a basement during the\nBattle of Wagram, attempting to protect what little hearing he had left. For 10 points, name this\ncomposer of the Pastoral and Choral symphonies as well as \"Fur Elise.\"",
      "answer": [
        "Ludwig van Beethoven",
        "Beethoven"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Neil Armstrong took a recording of theramin music and this man’s ninth symphony on Apollo 11. He\nwrote his twelfth string quartet while spending a summer in Spillville, Iowa, though his Slavonic Dances\nhonored Brahms and paid tribute to his native Bohemia. For ten points, name this Czech composer who,\nwhile visiting America, wrote his Symphony no. 9, “From the New World.”",
      "answer": [
        "Antonin Dvorak",
        "Dvorak"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One artist from this country classified his work as “stabiles” and “mobiles,” one of which consists of\naluminum fins suspended on steel wire. That artist from this country, Alexander Calder, also created Bent\nPropeller, which was destroyed when the Minoru Yamasaki-designed World Trade Center was attacked on\n9/11. For ten points, name this country, home of the Museum of Modern Art in New York.",
      "answer": [
        "United States of America",
        "USA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2003, a copy of this painting was covered by a blue curtain while Colin Powell addressed the United\nNations. On the left side of this painting, a bull stands over a woman who is holding her dead child. An\neye-shaped light bulb explodes in this painting above an impaled, screaming horse. For ten points, name\nthis painting inspired by the bombing of the title Basque town, a massive painting by Pablo Picasso.",
      "answer": "Guernica"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer popularized a percussion-heavy style music inspired by Janissary bands with an opera\nin which Belmonte rescues Konstanze from Pasha Selim’s harem. He included heavy Masonic symbolism\nin an opera in which Tamino overcomes a series of trials with the help of the title woodwind. For ten\npoints, name this composer of The Abduction From The Seraglio and The Magic Flute.",
      "answer": [
        "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
        "Mozart"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Xerxes the Great built a throne hall with one hundred of these features in Persepolis. The term\nentasis refers to the gradual decrease in these objects’ diameter as they rise, removing the optical illusion\nthat these objects bend inward. One style of these objects uses a scroll for the capital; in addition to that\nIonic type, these objects come in Doric and Corinthian orders. For ten points, name these architectural\nelements which usually bear the weight of a roof or ceiling.",
      "answer": [
        "columns",
        "pillars"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote the twelve-tone Connotations for the opening of Lincoln Center. He quoted\n“Camptown Races” in a composition that features a narrator reciting the Gettysburg Address. He\ndepicted a couple in western Pennsylvania in a ballet choreographed by Martha Graham that incorporates\nthe Shaker hymn “Simple Gifts.” For ten points, name this American composer of Lincoln Portrait and\nAppalachian Spring.",
      "answer": [
        "Aaron Copland",
        "Copland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This building’s gate includes the inscription “O Soul, thou art at rest” from the 89th sura of the\nQuran. It lies on the south bank of the Yamuna River, north of a garden with a pool reflecting this\nbuilding’s image. Its design includes four minarets, four small domes, and a large primary dome, and\nit was built as a tomb for Mumtaz, the emperor’s wife. Shah Jahan built, for ten points, what Muslim\nmausoleum in Agra, a masterpiece of Indian architecture?",
      "answer": "Taj Mahal"
    },
    {
      "question": "With Fred Archer, this artist gave pure white a value of ten in the Zone System. He showed\nJapanese-Americans at Manzanar in his work Born Free and Equal, and with Willard Van Dyke and\nEdward Weston, he formed the group f/64. This artist captured images of El Capitan and a round granite\nformation in Yosemite National Park. For ten points, name this photographer of Moon and Half Dome.",
      "answer": [
        "Ansel Easton Adams",
        "Adams"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer’s overture to Rienzi was performed at every Nuremburg Rally. This man attacked\nFelix Mendelssohn in the anti-Semitic tract On Jewishness in Music. He used the term “music dramas” to\ndescribe his operas. King Ludwig II’s castle Neuschwanstein [noysh-vahn-stein] was inspired by the operas\nof this man, which are often performed at his opera house in Bayreuth [bye-royt]. For ten points, name\nthis German composer of Lohengrin and The Ring Cycle.",
      "answer": [
        "Richard Wagner",
        "Wagner"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Bill Gates distributed pages of this man’s Codex Leicester [lester] as a Windows screen saver. This\nman wrote in reverse cursive in notebooks detailing water-walking shoes and an early helicopter design,\nand he superimposed two images of a man inscribed in a circle and square in his Vitruvian Man drawing.\nFor ten points, name this Italian Renaissance scientist and artist, whose non-journal works include the\nMona Lisa.",
      "answer": "Leonardo da Vinci"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man included two breakstrains in a piece written to honor a National Guard regiment, The\nGallant Seventh. He rejoined the military at the age of sixty-two when the US entered World War I and\ndeveloped a namesake variant of the tuba that wraps around the player. This leader of the US Marine\nBand wrote the “Liberty Bell” and a march to honor the American flag. For ten points, name this\ncomposer of the “Stars and Stripes Forever,” known as the “March King.”",
      "answer": [
        "John Philip Sousa",
        "Sousa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist showed three women crying as three brothers raise their arms toward swords in one work based on Roman legend. This Neoclassicist painter later depicted Napoleon with a hand tucked in his clothes in his study at the Tuileries [too-leh-ree], and on a rearing horse crossing the Alps. The subject of one of this artist’s works lies slumped over a desk in his bathtub after being stabbed by Charlotte Corday. For ten points, identify the French painter of The Oath of the Horatii and The Death of Marat.",
      "answer": [
        "Jacques-Louis David",
        "David"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A major genre innovation during this period was the concerto grosso (con-CHAIR-toe\nGROSS-oh), which was used extensively by Arcangelo Corelli. Another composer from this\nmusical period wrote the Goldberg Variations. For 10 points, name this period in Western music\nhistory that included Johann Sebastian Bach, and came between the Renaissance and Classical\neras.",
        "answer": "Baroque"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bach composed six concertos for Christian Ludwig, who held the symbolic title of\nMargrave of what state surrounding Potsdam, Germany?",
        "answer": "Brandenburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This song asks \"where is that band who so vaultingly swore\" and observes \"where the foes'\nhaughty host in dread silence reposes\" in its little-heard additional verses. The British bar song\nsong \"To Anacreon in Heaven\" was used to set the lyrics of this song. For 10 points, name this\nsong written during the British bombardment of Fort McHenry by Francis Scott Key.",
        "answer": "The Star-Spangled Banner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fort McHenry is found guarding the harbor of what major city?",
        "answer": "Baltimore"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist depicted Nazi concentration camp victims in The Charnel House. In the late 1940s,\nthis wealthy artist was the primary financial backer of the French Communist Party. An earlier\npolitical painting by him shows a lightbulb, a horse, and a screaming woman in memory of a\nBasque village bombed by the Nazis. For 10 points, name this creator of Guernica.",
        "answer": "Pablo Picasso, Picasso, Pablo Ruiz y Picasso"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "World War II itself caused the disappearance of many artworks, such as the Amber\nRoom formerly found in what city, which was besieged by Nazis for nine hundred days?",
        "answer": "St. Petersburg, Leningrad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's lavish spending on Italian art greatly expanded the Royal Collection. This man is\ndepicted with a stable boy, a horse, a walking stick, and red trousers, looking away from the\nThames (pr. TEMZ), in a portrait of him \"at the hunt.\" For 10 points, name this king whom\nAnthony van Dyck repeatedly painted prior to his execution in the English Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "Charles I of England",
          "Charles I"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other court painter made an insultingly realistic portrait of Charles IV of Spain\nand his family, as well as The Third of May, 1808?",
        "answer": [
          "Francisco Goya",
          "Francisco Jose de Goya y Lucientes",
          "Goya"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer incorporated \"Springfield Mountain\" and \"Camptown Races,\" along with\nexcerpts from the Gettysburg Address, into his World War II patriotic piece A Lincoln Portrait.\nHe scored ballets about Billy the Kid and about pioneers building a farmhouse in western\nPennsylvania. For 10 points, name this composer of Appalachian Spring.",
        "answer": [
          "Aaron Copland",
          "Copland"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As part of the same biographical project that led Copland to create A Lincoln Portrait,\nVirgil Thomson set poems by what author of Leaves of Grass?",
        "answer": [
          "Walt Whitman",
          "Whitman",
          "Walter Whitman"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Shortly after his death, this man was nominated for an Oscar for his work on Shall We Dance,\nfor which he wrote the song \"They Can't Take That Away From Me\" with his brother Ira. This\ncomposer used traffic horns in the score to An American in Paris and rumbas in his Cuban\nOverture. For 10 points, name this composer of the jazz concerto Rhapsody in Blue.",
        "answer": [
          "George Gershwin",
          "Gershwin"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gershwin adapted a play by DuBose Heyward into what opera, which has been both\npraised and criticized for its portrayal of black South Carolinians on Catfish Row?",
        "answer": "Porgy and Bess"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was approached by Thomas Edison's agent Theo Wangemann in 1889, leading him\nto make the first-ever audio recording by a leading composer. This composer relied on Martin\nLuther's translation of the Bible as the text for his German Requiem. For 10 points, name this\ncomposer whom Hans von Bulow first grouped with Beethoven and Bach as the \"Three Bs.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Johannes Brahms",
          "Brahms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brahms was born in what city, now the second largest city by population of Germany\nand once a major center of the Hanseatic League?",
        "answer": "Hamburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these people is the title character of an opera which was revised to add a “Polish act” and ends\nwith the Holy Fool lamenting his country’s fate in Kromy Forest. In another opera, Ivan Susanin sacrifices\nhimself for this title leader. The lead-up to the Time of Troubles was chronicled in Modest Mussorgsky’s\nopera about one of these monarchs, Boris Godunov. For ten points, Mikhail Glinka wrote an opera about\nA Life For what leaders of the Russian Empire?",
        "answer": [
          "tsars"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov’s opera The Tale of Tsar Saltan is best known for what virtuosic\norchestral excerpt in which the Tsar’s son is changed into an insect?",
        "answer": "Flight of the Bumblebee"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer wrote a piece originally intended for a “mechanical orchestra” to commemorate the\nBattle of Vitoria, Wellington’s Victory. He included a funeral march in a symphony which was dedicated\n“to the memory of a great man” after its original dedicatee, Napoleon Bonaparte, declared himself\nEmperor. This finale of this man’s last symphony was a setting of a Friedrich Schiller poem. For ten\npoints, name this composer of the Eroica Symphony whose Symphony #9 includes the “Ode to Joy.”",
        "answer": [
          "Ludwig van Beethoven",
          "Beethoven"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which five-movement symphony of Beethoven’s was subtitled “Recollections of Country Life”\nand included a musical depiction of a thunderstorm?",
        "answer": [
          "Pastoral Symphony",
          "Pastoral",
          "Symphony no. 6 in F Major",
          "6"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A piano suite by this man had six movements dedicated to friends killed in World War I. This\ncomposer of Le Tombeau de Couperin included a “Danse Generale” in the finale of his ballet Daphnis et\nChloe. He also wrote a piece which opens with a flute playing a melody that repeats in a long crescendo\nover a snare drum ostinato. For ten points, name this French composer of Bolero.",
        "answer": [
          "Maurice Ravel",
          "Ravel"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ravel wrote two of these pieces for soloist and orchestra, one of which, named “for the left\nhand,” was for Paul Wittgenstein, who had lost his right arm in World War I.",
        "answer": "piano concertos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer wrote a piece for the funeral of the Electress of Saxony Christiane Eberhardine known\nas the Trauerode. He wrote a piece to cure Count Kaiserling’s insomnia; that piece consists of an aria and\nthirty variations and was twice recorded by Glenn Gould. A collection of preludes and fugues in every\nmajor and minor key was composed by, for ten points, what Baroque composer of the Goldberg Variations\nand the Well-Tempered Clavier?",
        "answer": [
          "Johann Sebastian Bach",
          "Bach"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bach wrote this set of six orchestral works in an effort to gain employment with the margrave\nChristian Ludwig. Bach is believed to have played the harpsichord himself at the premiere of the fifth of\nthese works,",
        "answer": "Brandenburg Concertos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist created a work inspired by Goya’s 3rd of May, 1808 showing pregnant women with children\nin front of a futuristic firing squad; that work was a response to U.S. involvement in the Korean War.\nAnother work by this artist includes a flower growing from a sword held in a severed arm. A screaming\nhorse stands under a light bulb in that monochrome work by this artist. For ten points, name this Cubist\npainter who depicted the bombing of a Basque town during the Spanish Civil War in Guernica.",
        "answer": [
          "Pablo Ruiz y Picasso",
          "Picasso",
          "Pablo Picasso"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Picasso also created a series of etchings, similar in style to Guernica, named for “The Dream\nand Lie” of this Spanish general and leader.",
        "answer": [
          "Francisco Franco Bahamonde",
          "Franco",
          "Francisco Franco"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Many composers in this country were accused of “formalism” in the Zhdanov Doctrine. A composer\nhere withdrew his Mahler-inspired Fourth Symphony after the editorial “Muddle Instead of Music”\nattacked his modernist opera Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District. Socialist realism was the official\nartistic style of, for ten points, what nation where Dmitry Shostakovich fell out of favor with the\nCommunist Party under Joseph Stalin?",
        "answer": [
          "USSR",
          "Soviet Union",
          "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“Muddle Instead of Music” was published in what newspaper, the official publication of the\nSoviet Communist Party, whose Russian name translates to “Truth?”",
        "answer": "Pravda"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this era, Josquin des Prez (pr. JOHS-kin day PRAY) made advances in polyphony (puh-LIFF-uh-nee), and Giovanni da Palestrina wrote the (20 pts) ",
        "Pope Marcellus Mass. This era's music came under fire at the Council of Trent and was succeeded by the (10 pts) ",
        "Baroque period. For 10 points, identify this period in Western musical history in which motets and masses were the dominant form of music, and which shares its name with a \"rebirth\" in literature and visual arts."
      ],
      "answer": "the Renaissance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Buffalo Springfield insisted that the song \"For What It's Worth\" was about the Sunset Strip curfew riots and not this event. This event was the subject of Country Joe and the Fish's biggest hit. A veteran of this conflict is the subject of (20 pts) ",
        "Bruce Springsteen's \"Born in the USA,\" and a (10 pts) ",
        "protest against this conflict inspired Neil Young to write \"Ohio\" about the Kent State shootings. For 10 points, name this war which inspired copious protest music in the late 1960s."
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam War, Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An important 1878 piece for this instrument was composed for the virtuoso Joseph Joachim (pr. YO-zef YO-ah-keem). This instrument was played by a composer of (20 pts) ",
        "twenty-four caprices who allegedly made a deal with the devil, Niccolò (10 pts) ",
        "Paganini. Many valuable examples of this instrument were created by the master craftsman Antonio Stradivari. For 10 points, name this string instrument which an orchestra's concertmaster plays."
      ],
      "answer": "violin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a musical named for this dance, Judge Forestier (pr. for-ess-TEER) finally concludes\nthat \"It's All Right With Me.\" That Cole Porter musical discusses the scandal that this\ndance, which is in 2/4 time and based on the quadrille (pr. kwah-DREEL), caused when it was\nintroduced to (20 pts) ",
        "Paris in 1858. This dance first appeared in Jacques (10 pts) ",
        "Offenbach's Orpheus\nin the Underworld. For 10 points, name this characteristic French music hall dance involving\nwomen kicking their legs high."
      ],
      "answer": "the can-can"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This art movement included a literary section in which poets Hugo Ball and Tristan\nTzara worked. Artists in this movement produced \"ready-mades\" such as a bicycle (20 pts) ",
        "wheel and a urinal. This movement's name was supposedly chosen at the Cabaret Voltaire\nby sticking a (10 pts) ",
        "pen-knife into a French dictionary at random. For 10 points, name this\nabsurdist \"anti-art\" movement of the World War I era, which included Marcel Duchamp."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dadaism",
        "Dada"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one work set in this country, the title character sings “All alba vincero!” or “At\ndawn, I will win!” In another work set in this country, a woman interrupts a performance\nof The Red Detachment of Women. The aria (20 pts) ",
        "“Nessun dorma” is sung by Prince Calaf\nin this setting of Giacomo Puccini’s (10 pts) ",
        "Turandot. John Adams composed an opera about a 1972\nPresidential visit to, for ten points, what country where Richard Nixon met Mao Zedong?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "People’s Republic of China",
        "China"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A radiator of this color can be seen in the lower left Edward Hopper’s Automat, and a\nflag of this color flies atop of the mast of Bosch’s Ship of Fools. Gauguin painted a symbolic (20 pts) ",
        "Christ of this color, which joins black, red, and blue as the only colors in most (10 pts) ",
        "Piet Mondrian [PEET MOHN-dree-AHN] works. For ten points, name this primary color featured in Van\nGogh’s Sunflowers."
      ],
      "answer": "yellow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A parrot rests on a sign in one work by this artist, in which a cat, an ox, a rabbit, and\nan elk represent the Four Humors. A demon under a rainbow holds a sign bearing the title\nof this artist’s (20 pts) ",
        "Melencolia I. This artist incorrectly added a horn to his depiction of an\nanimal that had been given to Lisbon by Indian diplomats in 1515, and showed (10 pts) ",
        "Famine,\nWar, Plague, and Death trampling peasants in another work. For ten points, name this German creator\nof woodcuts like the Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse and Rhinoceros."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Albrecht Durer",
        "Durer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Artist George Catlin specialized in portraiture of these people. J.P. Morgan\nfunded Edward Curtis’ project to photographically document the lives of these\npeople. Korczak Ziolkowski began sculpting a (20 pts) ",
        "monument to one of these people\nin 1948; that unfinished monument is less than twenty miles from Mount Rushmore\non the (10 pts) ",
        "sacred Thunderhead Mountain. For ten points, name these people, including Crazy\nHorse, a member of the Oglala Sioux."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Native Americans",
        "American Indians"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In August 2015, one of these items was returned to NPR legal correspondent Nina\nTotenberg and her family 35 years after it was stolen from her father. In 2014, one of\nthese objects named “Lipinski” was stolen in Milwaukee after a performance of Olivier (20 pts) ",
        "Messiaen’s Quartet for the End of Time. Wood density and varnish quality have been\nproposed as explanations for the (10 pts) ",
        "brilliant sound of these instruments, which are roughly 300\nyears old. For ten points, name these instruments, reputed to be the finest-crafted violins in the world."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Stradivarius violin",
        "Stradivari",
        "Stradivarius instrument"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Neil Finn sang that this concept is “within” and “without” in the opening lyrics of\n“Don’t Dream It’s Over.” Paul McCartney wrote a song with this title while in a grounded\nplane in New York during the (20 pts) ",
        "September 11th attacks. It is “just another word for\nnothing left to lose” in Janis Joplin’s “Me and Bobby McGee,” and K’Naan sang “they call (10 pts) ",
        "me” this, “just like a wavin’ flag”. For ten points, name this political concept, the liberty to exert\nchoice and a lack of oppression."
      ],
      "answer": "freedom"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist began his career with historical images like The Misfortunes of the City of\nOrleans, and painted his aunt with her daughters and husband, Baron Gennaro (20 pts) ",
        "Bellelli.\nHis first work to be bought by a museum shows his uncle, Michel Musson’s, title Cotton\nOffice in New Orleans. A man wearing a black hat and a woman in a white dress sit in a\ncafe with a glass of the title (10 pts) ",
        "green beverage in this artist’s L’Absinthe. For ten points, name this\nFrench artist who painted many depictions of young ballerinas."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edgar Degas",
        "Degas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This painting is a companion to The Charge of the Mamelukes. It includes a cubic\nlantern that illuminates the pile of bodies below the group on the left. In this work, a (20 pts) ",
        "monk huddles near a man in white and yellow, who stands with his arms stretched upwards\nin (10 pts) ",
        "surrender. For ten points, name this painting in which a shadowy Napoleonic firing squad takes\naim at Spanish citizens in Madrid, a painting by Francisco Goya."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Third of May 1808: The Execution of the Defenders of Madrid",
        "The Third of May 1808",
        "El tres de mayo de 1808 en Madrid",
        "El tres de mayo de 1808",
        "Los fusilamientos de la montana del Principe Pio",
        "Los fusilamientos del tres de mayo"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician honored the first black heavyweight champion in his album A Tribute\nto Jack Johnson. He played flugelhorn in addition to his main instrument for a rendition\nof Rodrigo’s (20 pts) ",
        "Concierto de Aranjuez arranged by Gil Evans. This trumpeter added\nCannonball Adderly to his “first great quintet” and pioneered the genre of (10 pts) ",
        "cool jazz with\nalbums such as Sketches of Spain and songs like “Freddie Freeloader” and “So What”. For ten points,\nname this jazz trumpeter who recorded Kind of Blue."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Miles Davis",
        "Davis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One composer from this country wrote a microtonal work for 52 strings dedicated to\na city devastated by the atomic bomb, Threnody to the Victims of Hiroshima. Another\ncomposer born here wrote etudes nicknamed “Tristesse” and (20 pts) ",
        "“Black Key.” This\ncountry’s November Uprising also inspired the Revolutionary Étude of that composer. The (10 pts) ",
        "mazurka was a popular dance in, for ten points, what Eastern European home of Krystzof Penderecki\n[KRISH-toff pen-der-ETZ-ky] that inspired the piano works of its native, Frederic Chopin [sho-PAN]?"
      ],
      "answer": "Poland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A poet during this dynasty wrote “In these perilous times - I long to serve my sovereign”\nin the work “On the River,” written during a rebellion led by a Sogdian general. During\nthis dynasty, the poet of an (20 pts) ",
        "Ezra Pound-translated work, “A River Merchant’s Wife -\nA Letter” was exiled in the (10 pts) ",
        "An Lushan Rebellion. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty\nwhose poets included Du Fu and Li Po."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tang Dynasty",
        "Tang"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One work by this man shows a member of the White League shaking hands with the\nKKK above a shield that reads “Worse than Slavery.” Another (20 pts) ",
        "artwork by this man\nshows a man’s head replaced by a moneybag, and he depicted one institution as a tiger\nmauling a woman in a Roman Colosseum as faux-Emperor (10 pts) ",
        "Boss Tweed looks on. For ten\npoints, name this 19th century cartoonist for Harper’s Weekly who feuded with Tammany Hall."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Thomas Nast",
        "Nast"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city is home to the tomb of Ulysses S. Grant. An International style building in\nthis city designed by Ludwig Mies van der Rohe has a bronze and glass facade. This home\ncity of the (20 pts) ",
        "Seagram building includes a large park designed by Frederick Law Olmsted.\nOne building in this city has corner decorations modeled after (10 pts) ",
        "radiator caps, and a large\nart deco style “crown.” For ten points, name this city whose skyscrapers include the Chrysler Building\nand Empire State Building."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New York City",
        "New York",
        "NYC",
        "Manhattan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One opera set in this country includes an offstage chorus singing Psalm 104 and is the\nfinal entry in the “Portrait Trilogy.” Another opera set in this country was commissioned\nby Ismail Pasha to celebrate the opening of the Khedival Opera House and features the\ntitle princess singing (20 pts) ",
        "“O patria mia.” This country is the setting of a Philip Glass\nopera about a pioneering monotheistic ruler and a Verdi opera in which the title princess is\nburied alive with (10 pts) ",
        "Radames. For ten points, name this ancient civilization, the setting of Aida and\nAkhnaten."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Egypt",
        "ancient Egypt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Xu Bing used this art form to create the nonsensical Book From the Sky. Naskh and\nkufic are two forms of this art used by Muslim artists. This type of art was practiced on (20 pts) ",
        "tortoise shells in Shang dynasty China. Alcuin created one form of this technique known\nas the Carolingian miniscule. This technique is combined with (10 pts) ",
        "painting and illustration to\ncreate illuminated works like the Lindisfarne Gospels and Book of Kells as well as for transcribing the\nQuran. For ten points, name this visual art of elaborate decorative writing."
      ],
      "answer": "calligraphy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer’s Adagio and Rondo was written for an ensemble that included Benjamin\nFranklin’s glass armonica. His final three string quartets were written for Friedrich Wilhelm\nII of (20 pts) ",
        "Prussia, and his eleventh piano sonata ends with an imitation of Janissary bands\nfrom the Ottoman Empire. The impresario Johann Peter Salomon gave this man’s forty-first\nand (10 pts) ",
        "final symphony the nickname Jupiter. K¨ochel [ker-kel] numbers are used to catalogue the works\nof, for ten points, what composer of the “Rondo alla Turca” and Eine Kleine Nachtmusik?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
        "Mozart"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Tintoretto painted a dark version of this scene with a table running diagonally\nacross the canvas. In one version of this scene, the vanishing point was placed just\nabove the main subject’s head. That (20 pts) ",
        "fresco of this scene was protected by\nsandbags during World War II and shows twelve men seated on one side of a (10 pts) ",
        "dining table. For ten points, name this common artistic scene, painted by Leonardo da Vinci and\nnumerous others, depicting a meal the night before Jesus Christ’s crucifixion."
      ],
      "answer": "The Last Supper"
    }
  ]
}